Have you ever wondered
if there’s a natural way
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
The mind is a terrible
thing to waste,
so today we look at ways to
improve our cognitive function
and we start with a study
that measured the relationship
between exercise and
dementia prevention.
Based on a meta-analysis
of 20 studies,
mental performance
may be improved
with even modest weight loss
among overweight individuals,
though that may be due
not to the weight loss per se,
but rather
the prescribed exercise.
For example, one study
randomized obese elders
to one of four groups
for a year:
a weight-loss diet alone,
exercise without weight loss,
both, or neither.
Compared to the control group
that did neither,
global cognition improved
in all the three other groups,
but while weight loss
and exercise
beat out weight loss alone,
weight loss and exercise
didn't beat the exercise alone,
suggesting that exercise is
the most potent component.
The American College
of Sports Medicine
cites meta-analyses of dozens
of prospective studies
following tens of thousands
of people for years
that suggest
that those who are active
have a 38 percent lower risk
of cognitive decline
and a 39 percent lower risk
of developing
Alzheimer's disease.
And, apparently,
the more, the better.
Every extra 500 calories
expended a week
appears to correlate
with an additional
ten percent drop
in dementia risk.
However, even light
physical activity,
such as low-intensity walking,
or how yoga and tai chi
are often practiced
by older adults,
has been associated
with at least
some sort of cognitive gain
in about half of the studies
done to date.
If the relationship
between exercise
and dementia prevention
is cause and effect,
as much as 20 percent
of all cases
of Alzheimer's disease
in Western countries
may be attributable
to physical inactivity.
That would mean more than
a million cases of Alzheimer's
just in the U.S. alone.
As with all observational data,
though,
there's the potential
for confounding
or reverse causation.
Maybe there's a shared factor
causing both,
such as atherosclerosis,
contributing to both inactivity
and dementia,
or maybe those
genetically predisposed
to exercise a lot
also have a more robust
cognitive reserve
(though a Mendelian
randomization study
failed to find this).
Instead of inactivity
leading to dementia,
dementia could lead
to inactivity.
Prospective studies
following people over time
can show that the inactivity
does precede the dementia,
but both mental
and physical activity
can start declining
years before a diagnosis.
When researchers looked closely
at the data,
only inactivity
less than 10 years
before the diagnosis
was associated with dementia,
suggesting the causality
may indeed be backward.
When put to the test,
interventional trials show
physical activity
can be increased
in dementia patients,
which can improve
physical fitness,
but disappointingly did not
slow cognitive impairment.
Perhaps, we're just not
catching people early enough?
Adults with either
normal cognition
or mild cognitive impairment
randomized to exercise training
tend to improve
their cognition
compared to those ending up
in the less active
control groups.
A slight majority of studies
that concurrently tracked
brain imaging
found those randomized
to exercise
experienced a beneficial effect
on overall brain volume
as well as specifically
the hippocampus,
a part of the brain
that plays a critical role
in memory formation
and for which atrophy predicts
memory decline and dementia.
The seminal study,
"Exercise training
increases size of hippocampus
and improves memory,"
randomized older adults
to either a year
of supervised moderate
aerobic exercise (walking)
or a control group,
which instead involved a year
of stretching
and toning classes.
On average,
the hippocampus volume
of those in the control group
shrank 1.4 percent,
which is consistent
with the one to two percent
annual shrinkage
typical of old age.
In contrast,
over that same year
in the walking group,
their hippocampus volume
increased two percent,
which is like adding
a year or two of brain volume
(though may subsequently shrink
back to baseline
in as few as six weeks
of inactivity;
so you got to keep it up).
A similar study
that added a third group-
a resistance training arm-
found a similar
aerobic training reversal
of age-related shrinkage
in the memory centers
compared to the balance
and toning control group,
but unfortunately
there was no benefit seen
in the nonaerobic
strength-training group.
It's unclear exactly which type
of exercise is best,
but the cognitive benefit
of aerobic training
appears to be larger
than resistance training.
In most of the randomized
controlled trials
of older adults,
walking was the most frequently
chosen mode of exercise.
The best volume, duration,
frequency, or intensity
is also unknown.
Based on a meta-analysis
of nearly a hundred
randomized controlled trials,
more important
than session duration,
weekly frequency,
program duration, or intensity,
may be total training time.
However studies spliced it up,
it appeared to take exercising
for a total
of at least 52 hours
before a cognitive benefit
can be established.
In our next story,
we look at non-drug, non-supplement,
non-lifestyle approaches
to dementia prevention
and treatment.
In my book, How Not to Age,
I discuss the role
of drugs and supplements
and focus on diet
and lifestyle approaches
to the prevention and treatment
of cognitive decline,
but there are a few common
non-drug, non-supplement,
non-lifestyle approaches
to dementia treatment.
For example,
cognitive stimulation therapy,
which typically involves
group activities
and social interaction.
There have been at least 44
randomized controlled trials
of cognitive stimulation
including thousands
of participants.
ADAS-Cog, short for Alzheimer's
Disease Assessment Scale
Cognitive subscale,
is the most commonly used
measure of cognition
in clinical trials
of dementia treatment.
A clinically relevant
improvement
is often defined as a reduction
of four or more points
on the ADAS-Cog measure.
Regrettably, the attenuation
of cognitive decline
for most of the cognitive
stimulation studies
averaged only about two points.
Now you could argue,
look, any improvement
is better than nothing,
but unfortunately,
the cognitive effects
don't appear to generalize
to helping
with everyday life situations.
You can train people
to get better
at a computerized "brain game,"
but that doesn't necessarily
translate to other arenas.
Also, the marginal improvements
are temporary.
They don't seem to persist
once the intervention period
is over.
While cognitive
stimulation therapy
may have no significant
overall effect
on quality of life,
any kind of group therapy
has been shown
to improve
psychological well-being.
As social creatures,
social participation is
important for mental health
throughout the life course,
but there's
insufficient evidence
that it can improve or prevent
cognitive dysfunction.
Dementia is associated
with social isolation,
but this may be
reverse causation,
where the dementia leads
to social withdrawal,
instead of the other way around.
The same issue
comes up all the time
with those advocating
for "use-it-or-lose-it"
mental stimulation
to forestall decline.
For example, this review
in a peer-reviewed
aging journal suggested
that "if a person
solves crosswords
four times a week,
they can reduce their risk
of dementia by 47 percent."
Yes, doing
frequent crossword puzzles
is associated with lower
subsequent dementia risk,
but isn't it more likely
that those on the verge
of a dementia diagnosis
are less likely to be doing
crossword puzzles,
as a result of their declining
cognitive abilities?
Music therapy presents
a similar story
of improving well-being
without necessarily
affecting cognition.
Even in late stages
of dementia,
when verbal communication
is lost,
music can be enjoyed.
However, it does not seem
to improve brain function.
Most (five out of seven)
meta-analyses
of the 40+ interventional
clinical trials
of music therapy
for people with dementia
found no cognitive benefits.
And the few studies that did
found the effect
was short-lived,
disappearing
after one to three months.
Even though cognition
doesn't seem to be affected,
there still may be
positive effects
in terms of reducing agitation
and improving mood
and socialization.
One of the kookiest treatments
I ran across was cryotherapy,
also known as cryostimulation.
Those with mild
cognitive impairment
randomized
to short-term exposures
to extremely cold temperatures
experienced a transient boost
in general
cognitive functioning
(no longer apparent two weeks
after daily sessions ended).
Study subjects in shorts
and a T-shirt
were exposed to 58 degrees
below zero (-50 C)
for two minutes.
No, wait, that was
the placebo control group
exposed to "noncryogenic"
temperatures.
How low
did the experimental group go?
Two minutes
at more than 200 degrees
below zero (-130 C).
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.